Hello English learners, welcome back to
another great podcast here at EnglishPod,
my name is Marco and I'm Erica and today
we're going to be bringing you bad news.
That's right. Actually
what we're really going to
be bringing you is language
to talk about bad news.
Exactly. So maybe you have to give
bad news to your boss, to your parents.
I don't know somebody and we're going to
be teaching you how to do this in English.
Obviously it's always
difficult to tell somebody bad
news but in your second
language it's even harder.
So we're going to
try and help you today
with some great phrases
and vocabulary items.
We're not going to preview anything today.
Let's go directly to our dialogue where we
will be in a company and one of the employees
is going to be giving bad news to his boss.
So let's listen.
Now that we've been
over the gory details of our
disastrous first quarter,
Ed give us some good news.
How are things looking for
us in terms of sales this month?
Oh well, would you like the bad
news first or the really bad news?
What?
Ed, don't tell me you only have bad news.
Well sir, our sales have dropped.
No plunged.
50% in the past month alone.
We are currently overstocked and overstaffed
and our profits are falling fast.
The market is in recession
and we have no way of
moving our inventory
or getting rid of our staff.
If we consider redundancies,
it causes a fortune because
of the new regulations
governing compensation packages.
It's a real mess.
You're coming out loud.
How fast are we losing money?
Um, um, how can I put this?
Let's just say that at
this pace, we will be
filing for chapter 11 in
less than three months.
What?
Jeez, how can this
have happened?
So what's the bad news?
Oh, that's the really bad news.
Our suppliers suffered QC problems
and well, half of our production is faulty.
We're going to have to recall all items
sold in the last quarter and the worst part?
We're going to have to shoulder this cost.
Are you joking?
Get the supplier on the line now.
They have to assume the cost of this mess.
We try that, sir.
The factory has gone under and the
owner apparently has fled the country.
Well, we're doomed.
There's some really good news, though.
Really?
What? I got offered a new job.
Alright, it sounds like a pretty tough
time for this company, doesn't it?
But good news for the employee.
He won't be jobless.
Well, I guess he knows when to get out.
But why don't we take a look at some of
the language now in language takeaway?
Language takeaway.
We have five vocabulary items
and well, let's start with the first one.
Alright, so the boss, you
know, he's talking about
the gory details of our
disastrous first quarter.
So let's look at the phrase gory details.
Alright, so gory details.
Gory details.
This sounds kind of strange, gory details.
It seems very scary.
Well, the word gory comes from
gore, like blood and guts, right?
Exactly. That's why it
sounds a little bit scary too.
Yep, so gory details,
I mean, all the little
details of a negative or
shocking or bad situation.
Okay, so the gory details of the
meeting, so all the nasty negative stuff.
Or the gory detail, or you
could say the newspaper
reported all the gory
details of the murder.
Okay, very good, so gory details.
So the employee was talking about
how bad the company was doing.
And he mentioned this word redundancies.
Redundancies, they are
considering redundancies.
Okay, so redundancies, again, it's
based on the word to be redundant.
Alright, and that means
to not be needed anymore.
Okay, so redundancies
are basically firing people.
It's well, laying people off.
People that you don't need
anymore, they are redundancies.
Alright, so this is actually a British
term, redundancies to become redundant.
Because in American English,
you would just say layoffs.
Yep.
Okay, very good.
Alright, so moving on, they
were talking about redundancies
and maybe they should or
shouldn't lay some people off.
But one of the problems were the
regulations governing compensation packages.
Okay, so regulations governing
compensation packages.
Regulations governing something.
So we have a noun governing noun.
What does that mean?
Alright, so I think it would help
us to understand this a little better.
If we listen to some examples of
this pattern, noun governing noun.
Example one.
I don't agree with the regulations
governing income taxes.
People shouldn't have to give
away their hard-earned money.
Example two.
We need to protect the environment.
Therefore, there will be
new policies governing
corporate levels of
pollution starting next month.
Example three.
The lack of regulations
governing city
transportation has led
to many traffic accidents.
Okay, great examples.
Well, before we move on, this
compensation package is, I guess it's
all the things that the company
gives you when they lay you off, right?
Right, maybe a certain portion
of your retirement benefits.
Or months pay, etc.
Okay, compensation packages.
Alright, so moving
on to our next item on
language takeaway, we
have to shoulder the cost.
To shoulder the cost.
Alright, so if I shoulder
something, you have to carry it.
I carry it.
Yeah, that's a good one.
So basically it's the same
as the shoulder your body.
Yep.
So you carry this cost or
you carry this responsibility.
Yep.
So you might also hear shoulder the burden.
To shoulder the burden.
So it just means to
carry the responsibility.
Okay, to share it.
Yep.
Alright, interesting.
And we have one more
word on language takeaway.
And the factory has gone under.
To go under.
Alright, to go under.
When something goes under, a
company goes under, it goes bankrupt.
It goes bankrupt, so
it's not working anymore.
That's right.
Alright, so to go under.
Great vocabulary items here
on language takeaway today.
It's time for us to move
on to the next segment of
our show where we're
going to look at some phrases.
So let's start now with fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
Alright, so we've got some
phrases that you can use
when somebody's going
to tell you some bad news,
but also some phrases you
can use to deliver bad news.
Alright, so let's start
with our first phrase.
So the boss is getting ready
to prepare for this bad news.
And he says, "Lay it on me.
" He's like, "Okay,
lay it on me.
" Lay it on me.
So if I say this, lay it on
me and just saying, "Tell me.
" Exactly.
So give me the bad news.
Mm-hmm.
Alright, so lay it on me.
Very informal though.
Yeah, you're right.
It is kind of informal.
But our next phrase, you know, the
boss is hearing about all this bad news.
And he says, "For crying out loud."
"For crying out loud.
" "For crying out loud.
" Alright, so this is a very
common phrase of frustration.
Yep, right.
So why don't we listen to some examples to
kind of understand how we use this phrase?
Example one.
"For crying out loud."
When I tell you to have the
report done by Wednesday, that
means I expect it to be on
my desk by the end of the day.
Example two.
We've got to figure out a new
marketing strategy for crying out loud.
Example three.
"For crying out loud,
you just got your driving
license and you already
got in an accident."
So it kind of reminds me of, "Oh my God."
So you're frustrated,
you're saying this
phrase as, "Oh my God,"
or something like this.
Yeah, it's like, "Oh,
this is so annoying.
" Exactly.
"For crying out loud.
" Yep.
Alright, moving on to our third phrase.
"How can I put this?
" "How can I put this?
" So the boss asked him a direct question
and he said, "Well, how can I put this?"
So we use this phrase.
We want to say something
maybe a little bit more indirectly.
Right, so you're looking for words of
how you can make it softer or more polite.
Maybe the truth or what
you're about to say is a
little bit strong, so you
want to soften it up a bit.
Yeah.
Okay, so you say, "How can I put this?"
But then you have to complement
it with, let's just say that.
Let's just say that.
So how do we use this phrase?
So for example, somebody asks
me, "Well, what do you mean?
Why can't you come
on vacation with us?
" And I would say,
"How can I put this?"
Let's just say that in nine months you will
hear the pitter pattern of little feet.
Okay, so your girlfriend's pregnant.
Exactly.
So you're not saying,
"My girlfriend's pregnant.
" You're giving like a metaphor.
A metaphor of what's going on,
but you don't want to say it directly.
Yeah.
Another example.
I might say, "Let's just say that
Michael isn't doing a great job."
All right, so maybe there are very strong
reasons, or he's doing very, very poorly.
Right, but I'm just sort of not saying
it exactly directly that he's doing bad.
Okay, very good.
So it's a phrase that
you can actually use a lot.
And to be a little bit
more polite or a little
bit more indirect when you're
giving somebody some bad news.
Exactly.
To a nice sort of complementing
phrases for delivering bad news.
And why don't we hear them
one more time in the dialogue.
Now that we've been
over the gory details of our
disastrous first quarter,
Ed, give us some good news.
How are things looking for
us in terms of sales this month?
Uh, well, would you like the bad
news first or the really bad news?
What?
Don't tell me you only have bad news.
Well sir, our sales have dropped.
No plunged.
50% in the past month alone.
We are currently overstocked and overstaffed
and our profits are falling fast.
The market is in recession
and we have no way of
moving our inventory
or getting rid of our staff.
If we consider
redundancies, it causes a
fortune because of the new regulations
governing compensation packages.
It's a real mess.
You're coming out loud.
How fast are we losing money?
Um, um, how can I put this?
Let's just say that at
this pace, we will be
filing for chapter 11 in
less than three months.
What?
Jeez.
How can this have happened?
So what's the bad news?
Oh, that's the really bad news.
Our supplier suffered QC problems
and well, half of our production is faulty.
We're going to have to recall all items
sold in the last quarter and the worst part.
We're going to have to shoulder this cost.
Are you joking?
Get the supplier on the line now.
They have to assume the cost of this mess.
We try that, sir.
The factory has gone under and the
owner apparently has fled the country.
Oh, we're doomed.
There's some really good news, though.
Really?
What?
I got offered a new job.
All right, great.
So this topic of filing
for chapter 11 is actually
very recent, very common
now because recently
one of the biggest companies
filed for chapter 11 in the U.S.
Yeah, that's right.
But I often get confused
by the phrase to file
for chapter 11 versus
to file for chapter 13.
All right.
So in the United States,
the bankruptcy law has
different chapters or
different sections, right?
And chapter 11 is basically for companies
that run out of money that go bankrupt.
So they have to declare
themselves in bankruptcy.
Yep.
And so they file for chapter 11.
But what about chapter 13?
Chapter 13 is for people.
Ah, okay.
So people who have
large debts, maybe with the
car company or the telephone company and
they can't pay, they file for chapter 13.
They say, hey, I don't
have money, I can't pay.
All right.
And so I guess here
it's kind of a metaphor
again, you know, it's
this phrase to file for
chapter 11 or chapter
13, meaning bankruptcy.
Right.
And people will say personally
that they're filing for chapter 11.
Exactly.
Yep.
All right.
So this is an interesting
situation because
if you file for bankruptcy in
some countries, you can go to jail.
Ah, I read recently about this
happening in Dubai actually.
Exactly.
So there is prison for debts.
In the US, you don't
go to prison for debts.
Mm.
But what about, what about
in your countries listeners?
What happens when you
go into debt in your country?
Or what happens when a
company goes into bankruptcy?
Mm.
Let us know.
Come to our website, englishpot.com.
Leave your questions and comments.
And of course, Erica and I are
always there to help you out.
Thanks for downloading, you guys.
And until next time, goodbye.